All
right, good morning, גוט שלושה עשר בל״ג בעומר, Gut Shlosha Asar Bi-Lag
Ba-Omer, I guess. All right, we, today's דף daf is ס״ה, Samech
Hei, sixty-five, and we pick up at the bottom, at the top
of ס״ה, Samech Hei, we're actually a little bit ahead, at the
two dots. We were in the middle of a digression because we
had been discussing ways to deal with the non-Jew's ownership in the
courtyard, and the גמרא Gemara said, well, you know, if he's got
some hired hands working for him on his property and they're Jews,
they can just be considered as if they're owners of the property,
they can participate in the עירוב. Eruv. And that led to רב
נחמן Rav Nachman saying, oh, what a great discussion, you know, what
a great פסק. psak. And then he said something else about being
drunk and not פוסק, paskening, this is not a good, you know,
this is not a nice פסק. psak. And that led to the
גמרא's Gemara long whole digression about A, saying this is nice and
this isn't nice, which isn't appropriate, and B, issues about being drunk
and פוסק paskening and being drunk and דאוון, davening, and that's where
we left off yesterday. In fact, if somebody is drunk, they are
still liable for all of their actions,
and any business transaction they get into is binding, unless it gets
to the point that they're as drunk as לוט, Lot, where they
literally don't have no idea what they are doing. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara says, but they are also exempt, even less than that
they're exempt from דאוון, davening, because דאוון davening you need this, this
ability to be, have, you know, as if you were able to
stand before the king. So now we continue, about eight lines down,
ten lines down on ס״ה עמוד א׳ Samech Hei Amud Aleph by
the two dots. אמר רבי חנינא: Amar Rabbi Chanina: כל המפסיק מגן
בשעת גאוה סוגרין וחותמין צרות בעדו.
Kol hamaphsik magein b'sha'at ga'ava, sogrin
v'chosmin tzarot ba'ado.
So this is a very sort of poetic, terse statement. Anybody who
is מפסיק, maphsik, which גמרא Gemara will say means passes over, מגן,
magein, a shield or מגן magein of the at the time of
גאוה, ga'ava, they, it's you hand over and seal over the enemies
for his sake. So what does all of that mean? So רש״י
Rashi says מגן magein means מגן אברהם, Magein Avraham, and it's the
first ברכה. bracha. And as we know, the first ברכה bracha is
the one in particular where you have to have כונה kavana for.
And it says that if you pass over saying it, meaning you
don't דאוון daven because of גאוה, ga'ava, גאוה ga'ava here being associated
with being drunk, I guess being indulging in your own sort of,
you know, needs and not, not concerned for, for God. Also because
the גמרא Gemara often says that if you like eat before you
דאוון, daven, it's like, you know,
they quote a פסוק, pasuk, ואותי השלכת אחרי גוך, V'oti hishlachta acharei
gevecha, you have cast me behind your back. The גמרא Gemara in
ברכות Berachot says: אל תקרי גוך אלא גאך. Al tikrei gevecha ela
ge'echa. Not only your back, but your גאוה. ga'ava. אחרי שנתגאה עצמו
בבשר ויין, Acharei shenitga'eh atzmo b'basar v'yayin, after you've like sort of,
sort of took care of your own needs and you, you know,
you ate and you drank, now you're going to come and דאוון?
daven? So this whole idea of גאוה ga'ava in contrast to דאוון.
davening. So here, this is the way רש״י Rashi reads it, about
getting drunk. So first, you got drunk, and because of that you
are passing over saying מגן אברהם, Magein Avraham, you are not דאוון.
davening. Then, that for that reward, you will have your enemies handed
over, or your, you know, troubles handed into your hand, you know,
handed, meaning taken away. But then it's your enemies handed over. Presumably,
the reason it's mentioning the enemies is because מגן אברהם Magein Avraham
is, right, is protecting. Right, exactly. אשר מיגן צריך בידך. Asher migen
tzarecha b'yadecha. אנכי מגן לך, Anochi magein lach, you know,
right, exactly, אנכי מגן לך. Anochi magein lach. So the idea of
God protecting אברהם Avraham from his enemies. So here, if you don't
do that, don't say that ברכה, bracha, you don't say it for
the right reason, then you are rewarded with what that ברכה bracha
is about.
שנאמר, Shene'emar, as the פסוק pasuk says: גאוה אפיקי מגנים, Ga'ava aphikei
m'ginim, a גאוה ga'ava אפיקי aphikei of מגן, magein, of shield protection,
סגור חותם צר. sagur chotam tzar. You know, sealed and tied up,
bound and sealed, closed and sealed is the enemy. מאי משמע דהאי
אפיק לישנא דאעבורי הוא, Mai mashma d'hai aphik lishna d'avurei hu, where
do you see that this idea אפיק aphik means to pass
over? דכתיב: De-chtiv: אחי בגדו כמו נחל כאפיק נחלים יעבורו.
Achai bagdu k'mo
nachal k'aphik nechalim ya'avoru. My brothers, they,
their rebellion, their betrayal, is like a wadi, like the, like this
sort of, presumably means, you know, כאפיקים בנגב, k'aphikim ba'Negev, like we
say right in שיר המעלות. Shir HaMa'alot. The אפיקים aphikim is when
there is the, these, you know, when it rains during the dry
season, these wadis are dry. And if you've ever seen these wadis
in Israel, right, you know, they're basically like a big funnel. So
you get this flash flood because it rains and everything spills into
the wadi and it becomes this like flash flood. So that's why
we say כאפיקים בנגב, k'aphikim ba'Negev, you know, the returning from גלות
Galus will be like these, like when the, the flash flooding, you
know, it'll be all from, from nothing to everything, you know, in
this powerful rush of water. So anyway, so here, that's the simple
sense of this פסוק, pasuk, which he says כאפיקי נחלים יעבורו keafikei
nechalim yaavoru they will pass by like the, like the, like the,
you know, like the, like these rushes of the valley, like the
waters that are rushing through the ואדי, wadi, not the valley, the
ואדי, wadi, but anyway the גמרא Gemara connects the word אפיק afik
with יעבורו yaavoru which means to pass by. רבי יוחנן אומר, Rabbi
Yochanan omer, Rabbi Yochanan says, כל שאינו מפיק, kol she'eino mafik, whoever
does not מפיק. mafik. Now that could mean, it could mean that
means that you don't pass over, you're supposed to דאוון, daven, but
the גמרא Gemara understands it to, no, he means the same thing,
you're not supposed to דאוון, daven, but he explains the word מפיק
mafik differently. So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי מפיק? mai mafik? לישנא
דגלויי הוא. lishna degillui hu. So he understands the word מפיק mafik
means to expose. So you don't expose מגן, Magen, you don't articulate
מגן, Magen, rather you pass over. So it gets to the same
point, except he explains the word אפיק afik to mean to reveal
rather than to pass over. דכתיב, dechtiv, the פסוק possuk says, ויראו
אפיקי מים. vayeira’u afikei mayim. So again, notice אפיק afik in the
simple sense of the פסוק possuk here are these rushes of water,
you know, these rushing streams of water. But here it's just connected
to another word in the פסוק. possuk. He saw these אפיקי מים,
afikei mayim, these אפיקים afikim of water,
ויגלו מוסדות תבל, vayiglu mosdot tevel, and were revealed the foundations of
the, of, you know, of the world. So anyway, so because the
word אפיק afik is connected with to reveal, it means reveal. So
therefore the גמרא Gemara is saying if you don't reveal מגן, Magen,
same point, you don't say it, then you're rewarded. As opposed to
the other one who says if you pass over it. So it's
essentially the same point. So the גמרא Gemara says,
מכדי, michti, קרא kra משמע בין לומר בין לומר, mashma bein lomar
bein lomar, you know, so okay, in the end of the day,
the פסוק possuk means more or less the same thing. You're supposed
to pass over it or you're not supposed to say it. מאי
בינייהו? mai beinaihu? What difference, you know, what's the, you know,
what's the big difference? איכא בינייהו דרב ששת. ika beinaihu d'Rav Sheshet.
Ultimately, they would debate the case of רב ששת. Rav Sheshet. רב
ששת מסר שינתיה לשמעיה. Rav Sheshet masar shintei lishamei. רב ששת, Rav
Sheshet, when he was drunk, and I'm reading this all the way
רש''י Rashi reads it, when he was drunk, he would hand over
his sleep to his, to his attendant. Meaning he would say to
his attendant, you know, wake me when I'm, you know, give me
an hour to sleep, I'll sleep it off and then you can
wake me. So מר אית ליה דרב ששת ומר לית ליה דרב
ששת. mar it lei d'Rav Sheshet umar leit lei d'Rav Sheshet. One
holds like רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, one does not. So what does
this mean? So רש''י Rashi says if there's a proactive obligation to
pass over your drunkenness, it means you have to give it the
full amount of time. So to say, you know, wake me after
an hour or two, I'll be better by then, that's not enough.
You have to wait until you actually woke up on your own.
Whereas if you say the idea is not to reveal, it means
not to actively, when you are, you know, consciously drunk, not to
actively דאוון, daven, but it doesn't mean you have to like proactively
do, you know, make sure that it's, you know, let every, let
nature fully run its course. So therefore you can wake up after
a certain passage of time. You don't have to wait until you
wake up on your own. Very funny, like exactly how the, whether
you say it in the positive or the negative, one who, you
know, who passes over versus one who doesn't reveal, translates into this
issue here of רב ששת. Rav Sheshet. מהרש''א Maharsha also points out
that the גמרא Gemara earlier, you know, had this funny idea that
if it was exactly a רביעית, revi'it, then a little sleep works.
If it was more than a רביעית, revi'it, then it makes it
worse. And now we're finding that maybe if you wake up, if
you wake up on your own, maybe that'll be okay, or maybe
if you tell your attendant to wake you up after an hour
or two, maybe it'll be okay, which is right, similar to the
idea of walking. If you walk, it'll get worse unless you're riding,
or unless, you know, then, then after three מיל, mil, then it'll
get better even if you did drink a lot of wine. So
a lot of these sort of very subtle distinctions here, hard to
understand how it makes sense. Now the תוספות Tosafot points out רבינו
חננאל, Rabbeinu Chananel, excuse me,
with a different explanation. And he says like this.
He says the word כעבה ke'ava means your יצר הרע. yetzer hara.
And it sounded first like he was actually saying not even related
to being drunk. And the way he was reading it was the
following. What do you do? It's actually very interesting for all those
psychologists or Freudians out there. What do you do if you're battling
your יצר הרע? yetzer hara? Do you try to pass it over?
Mean like subjugate and sublimate it. So don't deal with it, just
try to push it down, right? That's the first, that you pass
over it, so sort of hide it and you push it down.
As opposed to the other approach, which is reveal. No, you actually
sort of get it out there and you deal with it in
a more direct way. So how's the way you sort of deal
with these desires? Now how does that then translate into the גמרא
Gemara about handing over to the sleep? So then תוספות Tosafot translates
it into the issue of being drunk. How do you deal with
being drunk? Do you try to like go to sleep and sleep
it off, or do you try to like walk it off, like
the גמרא Gemara yesterday? Deal with it out there in the open
or sort of let it just sort of take care of itself?
And that's how he sees whether that was, was going on, not
whether you have to, you know, wake up after two hours or
wake up on your own. But do you try to deal with
it by going to sleep, or do you deal with it directly
and confront it directly? So that's interesting because it's not just about
getting drunk, it's also about dealing with, you know, your various issues.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר רב חייא בר אשי
אמר רב, Amar Rav Chiya bar Ashi amar Rav, כל שאין דעתו.
kol she'ein da'ato. He needs to be preoccupied, then that's what they're
saying?
Is it not just about being drunk? But if you're—What do you
mean preoccupied about דאווענען?
Davenen? Yeah, we're going to get to preoccupied in a—No, it was
a little unclear as to what תוספות Tosafot got on—when he said
יצר הרע Yetzer Hara what he really meant was drunkenness. But
anyway,
it was unclear
whether the תוספות Tosafot was just saying something for הלכות
תפילה
Hilchos
Tefilla
or even something
for הלכות מדות.
Hilchos
Middos. You could look at תוספות. Tosafot. The beginning of it
certainly sounded more like a הלכות מדות Hilchos Middos discussion. Okay, so
anyway now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר חייא בר אשי
אמר רב: Amar Chiya bar Ashi amar Rav: כל שאין דעתו מיושבת
עליו. Kol she-ein da'ato meyushevet alav. Anybody—so before we spoke about being
drunk, right? And being drunk and not דאווענען, Davenen, being drunk and
not פסק-ענען, Paskenen, as I said before תוספות Tosafot pointed out תוספות
Tosafot the level for—that you need to be for דאווענען Davenen is
a higher one than for saying a ברכה. Beracha. For דאווענען Davenen
you have to be ראוי לעמוד לפני המלך. rauy la’amod lifnei hamelech.
And you know the גמרא Gemara before already introduced the idea that
it's not just drunkenness because at the top of the page we
said you know שכורה ולא מיין shikura velo miyayin that from the
time of גלות Golus began, at first the גמרא Gemara made a
very broad statement: Everybody's exempt from any sin they do because it's
like they're drunk. Then when it says, oh you know being drunk
doesn't exempt you, it says okay fine but at least everybody's exempt
from not דאווענען, Davenen, which basically puts on the table the idea
that it's not just drunkenness, it's distractedness. And as I mentioned also
yesterday when the גמרא Gemara talked about trying to walk it off,
it's תרדתא, tirdeta, it sort of, you know, makes you more distracted,
not necessarily more drunk. So we've introduced this idea that distractedness is
also a problem for דאווענען Davenen and for כוונה. Kavana. And that's
now the גמרא’ס Gemara’s going to turn to it. And it is
interesting to ask what is the כוונה Kavana that we require? Meaning,
one could say that being drunk is not even a question of
כוונה. Kavana. ראוי לעמוד לפני מלך Rauy la’amod lifnei melech means that
you know it's like if you were naked and standing and דאווענען.
Davenen. It's an inappropriate state to be, to be standing before God,
whether or not you're able to focus or not. That could be
one aspect of it. The other could just be the sense of
right, of being able to focus. Focus could be both in your
own mind, to have an awareness you're standing before God, so it's
not a question of appropriateness in terms of your state, but a
question about are you able to be aware and have the awareness
indeed. And one awareness is aware you're standing before God and the
other is awareness about what are the words you're saying and intending
the words you're saying. So the גמרא Gemara doesn't subdivide those, although
I certainly would say that one aspect of it is just the
state is inappropriate. But now because it's talking about distractedness, it's talking
about the כוונה. Kavana. So let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara
says like this. אמר חייא בר אשי אמר רב: Amar Chiya bar
Ashi amar Rav: כל שאין דעתו מיושבת עליו. Kol she-ein da'ato meyushevet
alav. Anybody who's—who's sort of mind is not settled, אל יתפלל, al
yitpalel, you should not דאווען. Daven. משום שנאמר, Mishum shene'emar, because it
says בצר אל יורה. Batzar al yoreh. In anguish you should not
rule. And somehow rule becoming—becoming—so
fine—become—so going from פסק Psak to an issue of דאווענען. Davenen. The
only problem is you'll notice there's not a little circle by it
and there's not a little marginal note that says where this פסוק
Pasuk is. So if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says—yep,
so רש"י Rashi says בצר אל יורה. Batzar al yoreh. This is
about ten lines down in the narrow lines. רש"י Rashi says: בדקתי
אחר המקרא הזה, Badakti achar hamikra hazeh, I've looked for this פסוק,
Pasuk, וזה אינו בכל הכתובים, vezeh eino bechol haktuvim, it's nowhere in
any of the scriptures. ושמא בספר בן סירא הוא, Veshema besefer Ben
Sira hu, maybe it's in בן סירא. Ben Sira. Because the גמרא
Gemara does sometimes quote פסוקים Pesukim from בן סירא Ben Sira and
actually says דכתיב, Dechtiv, as it's written. So it actually treated it
in this sort of
quasi ספרי קודש Sifrei Kodesh type of a status. תוספות Tosafot has
a whole series of speculations about how this might be a paraphrase
of another פסוק Pasuk and not actually a quote from בן סירא.
Ben Sira. Okay, but anyway the גמרא’ס Gemara’s going to go back
to these words of בצר אל יורה. Batzar al yoreh. רב חנינא
ביומא דרתח, Rav Chanina beyoma dertach, רב חנינא Rav Chanina when he
would get angry, לא מצלי, lo matzli, would not דאווען. Daven. You
know, sometimes people they're so angry they can't think of anything else.
You know, they're just so—so taken by their anger, you know, so
overwhelmed by it. Because he said—What the whole day? What the whole
day? For some people that's the way it is. Maybe anyway after
a while it was after זמן תפילה. Zman Tefilla. אמר בצר אל
יורה. Amar Batzar al yoreh. When you're in anguish you should not
rule. And again interestingly translating a rule into דאווענען. Davenen. Particularly fascinating
if here it's not even really a פסוק Pasuk and it's some
paraphrase but they're doing a paraphrase of something that's about פסק-ענען Paskenen
rather than about—rather than about דאווענען. Davenen. דכתיב Dechtiv is what it's
written. Notice again the דכתיב. Dechtiv. מר עוקבא ביומא דשותא, Mar Ukva
beyoma deshusah, when it was a day of the—of the southern wind,
which was a—which was a very like—you know,
windy and hot day and a day that was hard
to—hard to focus. So לא הוי נפיק לבי דינא. Lo havi nafik
l'vei dina. Now here finally we're getting to פסק-ענען, Paskenen, not just
דאווענען. Davenen. He wouldn't go to the בית דין Beis Din to—to
be a דיין. Dayan. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק: Amar Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak: הלכתא בעיא צילותא. Hilchasa ba'ya tzilusa.
When you give הלכה Halachic rulings it requires clarity, כיומא דאסתנא, kiyoma
d’astana, like a day of the northern wind. So that could be—רש"י
Rashi either says it literally means when the northern wind blows, it's
a cooling wind and that settles your mind and you're able to
focus and דאווען, Daven, or the מהרש"א— Maharsha It says כיומא *K'yoma*
דאסתנא *D'istana*, it means like it's like on a, when it's like
a beautiful day out, like a beautiful spring day. You need that
type of a clarity, not a cloud in the sky. So when
there are things that are distracting you, it's not a good day
to be sitting in judgment.
Okay, now the difference, of course, about דאווענען *davening* and judgment is
two. Number one, judgment you would think you would need more clarity,
at least the way we act, we would think we need more
clarity because we know how much כוונה kavana *kavanah* we normally have,
which I'll get back to. Number two, if you're not פסקנען *paskening*,
presumably it could be postponed. You could have the case some other
day, somebody else could פסקן pasken, *pasken*. But if you're not דאווענען
*davening*, you're actually foregoing your obligation. And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
still indicating that that's what you should be doing, like the whole
גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* before about passing over saying מגן אבות *Magen Avos*,
passing over דאווענען *davening*. Better to not דאווען daven. *daven* when you
shouldn't be, you know, and miss, rather not to דאווען daven *daven*
than to דאווען *daven* in an inappropriate way. אמר אביי *Amar Abaye*.
Now אביי *Abaye* says, now we're going to talk about people's distractibility.
So said אביי *Abaye*, אם אמרה לי אם *im amra li em*,
if my mother would say to me—now mother, his mother here meant
the woman who raised him, his nursemaid, he's always quoting her in
various different, you know, aspects, a lot having to do with certain
healing issues and רפואות *refuos* in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, medicinal issues—anyway,
if my mother would say to me, קרי כוזא *karei kucha*, bring
me the dip, so לא No, תנאי *lo tanoei*, I can't learn
anymore, like it would disrupt my learning and I'd be too distracted.
Now did it mean I'd be so distracted until I actually took
care of it, or did it mean just it interrupted me and
I needed complete silence and if anybody said anything to me in
the middle, it would throw me off my stride? It's not exactly
clear, but the point is very much about this issue of the,
you know, the concerns of distractibility. אמר רבא *Amar Rava*. Now רבא
*Rava* said—so notice we're going from דאווענען *davening* to פסקנען *paskening* to
now just learning. אמר רבא *Amar Rava*, said רבא *Rava*, some say
רבינא Ravina. *Ravina*, איטרצתן כינה *itratztin kina*, if a louse bites me,
לא תנאי *lo tanoei*, I can't learn. I mean, I can associate,
I can identify with that because I hate mosquito bites. You know,
oh my god, and you scratch it and it gets worse, you
don't scratch it and your head's on the thing. So anyway, he
says like when that happens, I'm just so distracted, I can't focus
the way I need to. Okay. It's
very humanizing here, you know, you think these greatest of all the
אמוראים *Amoraim*, and here they say if I have to deal with
a mosquito bite, it just completely throws me off my stride.
Yeah, yeah, and it was always the blood, it was a blood-allowed?
I know, I know, I'm saying. So how, it must have been
very hard for them to find time to learn if any time
he was
interrupted.
But it should be the opposite, that if you're, with some people,
if you're upset, that's when you should pray.
Yeah, well, we're talking about learning, not praying.
But before we said—oh, you mean,
בצער אל יורה *betza'ar al yoreh*? You know, that's an interesting point.
בצער אל יורה *betza'ar al yoreh*, agitated.
So you know, that's an interesting point that I'll say something about
that, which is, there's a מחלוקת *machlokes*, first of all, the פסוק
pasuk *pasuk*, whatever it was that they were quoting, said should not
rule, and notice now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has shifted to this
issue about focus and distractibility when it comes to learning and פסקנען
*paskening* and moved away from דאווענען *davening*. But it did start with
the issue about דאווענען *davening*. And, you know, there's a מחלוקת *machlokes*
between רמב״ם Rambam, *Rambam* and רמב״ן *Ramban* whether there's a מצוה *mitzvah*
to דאווען *daven* on a daily basis. The רמב״ם Rambam *Rambam* says
it says, you know, ועבדתם את ה׳ אלקיכם בכל לבבכם *va'avadtas es
Hashem Elokecha bechol levavecha*, איזו היא עבודה שבלב הוי אומר זו תפילה
*eizehu hi avodah shebelev? Zu tefillah*, which is a דרשה *drasha* in
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, serve God with your heart, what is service
of the heart? It's prayer, and the רמב״ם *Rambam* understands that there's
a biblical obligation to pray daily. And the רמב״ן *Ramban* says there's
no biblical obligation to pray daily, but he says there is an
obligation to pray בעת צרה *be'eis tzarah* when you are in a
time of affliction. Okay? Because there you could even make the theological
point that if you're being beset by affliction and you're not turning
to דאווען *daven*, what does that say about your basic, you know,
belief in God and theology and your sense
of your dependence on God and so on? So the רמב״ן *Ramban*
says that actually the only time there's a מצוה *mitzvah* to pray
is when it's a time of צער *tzar*. And here the גמרא
Gemara. *Gemara* says צער *tzar*, don't pray. But I think the difference
is that one is a צער *tzar* being beset by affliction. Here
we're talking about the issue of just being unable to focus. The
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* translated it in a very particular way, you're right,
it said, you know, it said you're not able to focus your
mind or you're so angry you can't focus on the words you're
saying. But you make an excellent point. I mean, a certain type
of affliction, beset by external afflictions, and you have a desire to
turn to God, that according to the רמב״ן *Ramban* is exactly when
you have a מצוה *mitzvah* to pray, exactly under those circumstances.
But it's interesting also, you know, with the drunkenness and, you know,
not praying, I mean, it was your, if you will, fault you
got drunk. Here you're being rewarded for not praying?
Not rewarded, you're being told that in this situation right now, the
better thing to do is not to דאווען *daven* than to דאווען
*daven* in an inappropriate way.
But it's not like you get off without punishment, because God, you
know, closes all the avenues from you?
At the beginning of next—all right, it's a good point. Also, getting
drunk in the time of the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* was not necessarily
going to a bar and having drink after drink. It was when
you had your meal, you drank wine. So, you know, it was
maybe a common type of a concern, and you know, that was
your primary beverage.
You should just דאווען *daven* first and then have your meal.
All right, so let's keep on going. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*
says like this. מר Mar
בריה דרבינא, מר the son of רבינא. Ravina And some say, by
the way, the previous statement was רבינא Ravina, about the louse. עבדא
ליה אמיה זיין מני לזיין יומי. Avda lei imei zayin manei lezayin
yomei. His mother made for him seven garments for the seven days
of the week. Now presumably it's because fresh garments have less infestation
of lice. So if this was רבינא, Ravina so maybe maybe רבינא's
wife should have made it for him and not just for the
son, but okay, presumably a similar issue. אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav
Yehuda, לא איברי ליליא אלא לשינתא. lo ivri leilya ela leshinta. The
reason God created night for sleeping.
And so we'll see what that's about. אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish
Lakish, לא, לא איברי סיהרא אלא לגרסא. lo ivri saira ela legirsa.
But God created the moon for learning. So this was about what
do you do at night. So one is saying, you know, I
can't learn, I can't learn well at night, you know, you have
to have artificial lighting or
whatever, so night you're supposed to sleep, you focus on your learning
during the day. And the other, oh there's the moon out. Now
תוספות Tosafot was a little bit disturbed by the idea that you're
not supposed to do any learning at night. So if you take
a look at תוספות Tosafot אלא לשינתא, ela leshinta, this one line
תוספות, Tosafot, he says כמו לילי תקופת תמוז, kemo leilei tekufat Tammuz,
it means summer nights. So you have, you know, 16 hours in
the day to learn, so then sleep at night. But if you
got a winter night, of course, you're supposed to be learning at
night as well. המהרש"א HaMaharsha says that they're really not disagreeing, that
when the moon is out, you know, and it's you have good
moonlight then you'll learn, and when it's pitch dark then you sleep.
And he was probably more accustomed to work at night because of
his background.
Oh,
that's well said. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish the bandit maybe, you know,
enjoys the night. Okay, so anyway, so
אמרו ליה
לרבי זירא, Amru lei leRabbi Zeira, they said to
רבי זירא, Rabbi Zeira, מחדדין שמעתתך, mechadadin shematatach, your, you know, your
teachings, your learnings are very sharp. How did you get to have
such insight and be so sharp about it? אמר להו, Amar lehu,
he said back, דיממי נינהו, deymamei ninhu, oh, that's the stuff I
learned during the day, that's when I really, you know, you know,
get depth into and understanding into what I'm learning. So אמרה ליה
ברתיה דרב חסדא לרב חסדא, Amra lei bartei deRav Chisda leRav Chisda,
so notice he says, it's not like I don't learn at night,
but you know, in terms of the real understanding I get during
the day. So the daughter of רב חסדא Rav Chisda says to
רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, לא בעי מר מינם פורתא? lo ba'ei Mar
minam purta? Does the Master not need to sleep a little bit?
So so I mean he was up there straight in the middle
of the night learning straight through the night.
And we don't appreciate, I should say, you know, how artificial lighting
has completely changed our, you know, our structure of the day and
our rhythms. I mean, you know, people used to work from sun
to sun, right? You know, that's that old, that's that line, right?
What is it? A man works from sun to sun, but a
woman's work is never done.
Well, as defined by תוספות Tosafot as summer nights. Well, very
right, anyway, but totally people would work within the rhythms of the
sun. So learning in the night and doing anything in the night
other than eating and going to sleep was a חידוש. chiddush. Yeah.
They did have candles. They did have candles, but it was a
lot more difficult to try to do things by candlelight than it
is by nice clean artificial light. Anyway, so he said, don't you
have to sleep at all?
So
אמר לה, Amar lah, he said to her, השתא אתו יומי דאריכי
וקטיני ונינום. Hashta atu yomei de'arichi veketini veninum. Don't worry, soon enough
will come the days that are long and short and we'll have
plenty of time to sleep. So what he presumes is when we're
dead. So what does long and short mean? So he means like
we'll be רש"י Rashi says, what does רש"י Rashi say long and
short mean?
They're long to sleep and they are very and they are short
for doing מצוות, mitzvot, actually they don't exist for doing מצוות. mitzvot.
Anyway, but somehow he meant, you know, don't worry we'll have plenty
of time to sleep when we're dead, which you know, they tell
a famous story about that about the Vilna Gaon, that he hadn't
seen his sister for like, you know, for like what was 20
years or something. Anyway, then she came to visit him and, you
know, and he looked up and he said hello and went back
to his learning. So she started crying, she said I traveled all
this distance to see you, we haven't seen each other for 20
years, says this is you just say hello? He said we'll have
plenty of time to talk in עולם הבא, Olam HaBa, now we
have to learn. So, which you know, is held up as this
like ideal, right?
What, that he's
a bit of a meany?
You know, and we discussed this before I think with a גמרא
Gemara that talked about like abandoning your wife and kids in order
to learn. רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Right, well and there are these
different ethos. I mean the Vilna Gaon writes very much about about
how, you know, a person is supposed, the strength of character is
that you don't listen to your wife and kids who want, you
know, to support them and you completely abandon them so you could
all you could do is sit and learn. You know, and then
there are other גמרות Gemarot that speak very much about how you
have to, you know, have to prioritize and certainly, you know, the
whole issue about do you first get married or do you first
learn is a question about once you get married you have real
responsibilities and you can't ignore those responsibilities and your בין אדם לחבירו
bein adam lechavero and balancing it with your sort of obligations to
God. You know, I sometimes say that a nice a nice metaphor
for this is or whatever model for this is פרשה parsha we
read not too long ago by the כהן, Kohen, right, where it's
the normal כהן... Kohen... he's the one that stayed in the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash when his relatives died, but the כהן גדול, Kohen
Gadol, he's the one that stayed in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
So one person in a generation could be the וילנא גאון Vilna
Gaon and the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and, you know, abandon all
else, you know, because of what they can achieve, you know, in
learning. Everybody else has to live in this world and has to
balance their, you know, their responsibilities in multiple ways. Anyway, here at
least while the reason I just I went off on a tangent
because it's such a famous story about the וילנא גאון Vilna Gaon
and here it actually originates in this גמרא, Gemara, but at least
in this גמרא Gemara he wasn't disregarding his other responsibilities, you know,
she just says don't you have to sleep at all and he
says, eh, we'll sleep later. So anyway, okay.
אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, אנא פועלי
דיממי אנן. ana poalei d'yimami anan. And so again, but interesting the
גמרא Gemara keeps on quoting, you know, different opinions about this. Should
you be learning at night or not? So רב נחמן בר יצחק
Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak says we're day workers, you know, which obviously
evokes the line from פרקי אבות, Pirkei Avos, which is, you know,
היום קצר והמלאכה מרובה והפועלים עצלים ובעל הבית דוחק, Hayom katzar v'hamelacha
merubah v'hapoalim atzelim u'ba'al habayis dochek, you know, the פועלים poalim are
lazy, the day is short, you know, the right, you know, the
taskmaster is demanding more work, you know, but here it's saying okay
fine but the day is short, we're day workers, at night we
have off, so that is for sleeping. Okay, good thing they didn't
have TV. All right. Anyway, so we're day workers. רב אחא בר
יעקב יזיף ופרע. Rav Acha bar Yaakov yazif u'para. רב אחא בר
יעקב, Rav Acha bar Yaakov, he would, the way the מהרש"א Maharsha
explains this is, he would get his best learning done in the
day, but if something came up in the day, he would borrow
against it and pay off, meaning he'd make up the time at
night. So that night would not be the ideal time, but he
would make that up, use that to make up if something happened
during the day. Okay, so that was a fascinating digression about the
issues about the need for, you know, good conditions to learn, and,
you know, in a real interesting sense of like do you try
to learn during times which are less than ideal, how do you
structure your day in terms of that? So now the גמרא Gemara
says, אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, back to davening, הבא מן
הדרך אל יתפלל שלושה ימים. haba min haderech al yitpallel shelosha yamim.
After you've returned from a journey, now again for them it was
not just landing in the airport and taking a cab home, you
know, a journey was a major endeavor. So for three days you
shouldn't daven, because you'll have to, you know, you just have to
get reacclimated and settle back down and so on. שנאמר, Shene'emar, ואקבצם
אל הנהר הבא אל אהוא ונחנה שם ימים שלושה ואבינה בעם, Va'ekbetzem
el hanahar haba el Ahua vanachana sham yamim shelosha va'avina ba'am, I
gathered them to the
river and we rested there for three days and I understood. So
it takes me three days before you can start having your understanding
back. The מהרש"א Maharsha points out actually that the next פסוק pasuk,
refers to them praying, so therefore after three days you would pray.
So אבוה דשמואל, Avuha d'Shmuel, the father of שמואל, Shmuel, כי אתי
באורחא לא מצלי תלתא יומי, ki ati b'orcha lo matzli tlata yomei,
when he came from a journey he wouldn't pray for three days.
שמואל Shmuel himself, לא מצלי בביתא דאית ביה שכרא, lo matzli b'veita
d'is bei shichra, in a house in which people had been drinking.
Presumably, maybe, you know, that the smell of the alcohol would be
too distracting, or just the environment would just set him off.
Like different than צואה tzoah or something, right?
Right, well yeah, but that's just שמואל, Shmuel, there's not an objective
הלכה halacha about the fact that drinking had occurred but for שמואל
Shmuel that was too distracting. רב פפא לא מצלי בביתא דאית ביה
הרסנא. Rav Pappa lo matzli b'veita d'is bei harsana. רב פפא Rav
Pappa wouldn't daven in a house that had in it fish fry,
this fish dish, which was so smelly, it was disgusting, he couldn't
daven. So therefore so that at least I think we can identify,
relate to more than the drinking one. Like a real disgusting smell
and I my, you know, good thirty years ago, my first year
in Israel, my brother went to ישיבת שעלבים, Yeshivat Sha'alvim, which is
at a קיבוץ, kibbutz, and he says, you know, when it came
time, you know, and it was so he says there was this
terrible smell, you know, from the cows or whatever. So they went
over to one of the רבנים rabanim and he said, like, are
we allowed to daven with this smell? And he said, what smell?
So, what you're used to. So anyway, all right. So אמר רבי
חנינא, Amar Rabbi Chanina, כל המתפתה ביין... kol hamitpateh b'yayin... So before
we go on about this, I do want to say something. So
what does this mean literally, come back from a trip you can't
daven? Do we really say if it's distracting you can't daven? So
I want to just read to you a interesting, like, רמב"ם Rambam
and what do you call it, רמב"ם Rambam and ראב"ד, Ra'avad, which
is also reflected in a תוספות Tosafos as well, which is how
do any of these things apply to us nowadays?
So, hold on.
I thought it was a
ראב"ד. Ra'avad. I'm not seeing it as a ראב"ד, Ra'avad, it's definitely
a תוספות Tosafos throughout ש"ס. Shas.
Just give me one second here. The basic point is that a
lot of the ראשונים Rishonim say
that none of this applies nowadays because because we don't have any
כוונה kavanah, even when we're not traveling. So our threshold of... what
we consider to be, if we really demanded the right type of
כוונה, kavanah we would never דאווען. So our threshold of what we
have redefined as being acceptable כוונה has gotten a lot lower, and
therefore we don't have all of these exemptions that are in the
גמרא. Gemara. But it does make you wonder, that's basically how we
פסקן, pasken. but it does make you wonder, you know, whether if
somebody really is extremely distracted and can't be מתפלל, mispallel, you know,
whether they actually, we should tell them don't דאווען or not. Did
you find the חזון איש?
Chazon Ish? What? Does this apply to a חתן? Chassan?
Well yeah, but a חתן Chassan has more to do with עוסק...
Osek... the גמרא Gemara debates whether the חתן Chassan is about טרדא
Tirda or about עוסק במצוה. Osek Be-mitzvah.
So, alright, anyway, I thought I remembered it being a ראב״ד, Ra'avad,
which I'm not finding right now. I see the רמב״ם, but I
don't see the ראב״ד. Ra'avad.
Yeah, I saw... right... you know where it came from, but it
says you'll only open it up at the daytime, then after sunset
he pops out that way.
Right, right. So it starts in a תוספות, Tosfos, right, it starts
in a תוספות, Tosfos, it's paskened in the שלחן ערוך. Shulchan Aruch.
But, but I just thought I would quote a רמב״ם ראב״ד, Ra'avad,
but I'm not finding the ראב״ד Ra'avad right now.
Right,
ירידת הדורות, yeridas hadoros, something like that. Something like that. Right. Okay,
so now let's continue in the גמרא. Gemara They had a
mosquito bite... No, no, no, that was learning. That was learning. Okay,
now the ברייתא baraisa says like this. אמר רבי חנינא, Amar Rabbi
Chanina, okay, כל המתפתה ביינו, Kol hamispateh be-yeino, anybody that can be
sort of appeased with their wine, so you know, somebody's really angry
at someone, so he waits until they're drinking, and you know, and
he's in a better and happier mood, and then he makes up
with him. יש בו מידת קונו. Yesh bo midas kono. So you
are similar to your Creator, that you're able to be appeased with
your wine. שנאמר וירח השם את ריח הניחוח, Shene'emar vayaryach Hashem es
reiach hanichoach, God smelled the pleasing smell of the sacrifice and He
said I will no longer curse the Earth, which is a very
bizarre גמרא, Gemara I mean it's a highly anthropomorphic פסוק, one of
the more anthropomorphic of the פסוקים. pesukim. And here it says, Oh
you know, if you actually do that, you wait until you're in
a good mood, God was smelling good stuff, drinking good wine. Now,
you know, you're acting it's like imitatio Dei, you're so...
so I'll be like God, I'll go to a barbecue, I'll get
in a good mood, and then I'll be able to be... so
what does that mean? So the מהרש״א Maharsha explains, again I don't
know if it's פשט, pshat, but the מהרש״א Maharsha explains that the
emphasis is on ביינו, be-yeino, meaning if I'm mad with you, and
you take me out and you wine and dine me, that's one
thing. But let's say you wait until I'm drinking my own wine,
and then... and then you come and you... and you try to
make up with me. So you didn't even put me in the
good mood, I'm drinking my own wine, but if I'm willing at
that stage to be generous enough, so that's like God, because when
you give God a sacrifice, you're really just giving God what is
God's. So therefore, but God's willing to give... give you credit for
that. That's how the מהרש״א Maharsha explains. Again, I don't know if
it's פשט pshat or not, but it makes the גמרא Gemara a
little more understandable. Okay, אמר רבי חייא, Amar Rabbi Chiya, כל המתיישב
ביינו, Kol hamisyashev be-yeino, anybody who is settled when they drink wine,
meaning who does not... you know, who can... anybody who can, what's
it called? Hold his liquor? Anybody who can hold his wine? יש
בו דעת ע׳ זקנים, Yesh bo da'as ayin zekeinim, has the wisdom
of the seventy elders. Why? יין ניתן בע׳ אותיות. Yayin nitan be-ayin
osiyos. יין Yayin is given in seventy letters, which really means the
גימטריא gematria of יין yayin is seventy, יוד יוד נון. yud yud
nun. וסוד ניתן בע׳ אותיות, Ve-sod nitan be-ayin osiyos, and the גימטריא
gematria of סוד, sod, secret, is seventy letters. נכנס יין, Nichnas yayin,
wine goes out, יצא סוד. yatzah sod. Goes in, wine goes out,
secrets come out. So if you're able to hold your liquor, hold
your wine and not start sort of to jabber and say private
things, then you will hold... then it's like the other seventy, the
seventy elders and you have... and you are... a repository for their
wisdom. אמר רבי חנין... Amar Rabbi Chanin...
this is a popular saying, but it means something different, right?
It means that wine is a good way of getting you to
open up. Right. So it's good, the secrets coming out in a
good way, in a... right. So that's true. But here now the
גמרא, because people also blabber things they're not supposed to blabber when
they get drunk.
That's a good point.
Wisdom, right, wisdom. רש״י Rashi says יצא סוד וזה ע׳ ולא יצא
סודו שקול הוא כסנהדרין. yatzah sod ve-zeh ayin ve-lo yatzah sodo shakula
hu ke-sanhedrin. It's not clear, right, you know, רש״י Rashi sort of
means, says like, you know, you're equal because you held it in.
But you're probably right, it could mean that סוד sod here has
a sense of תורה Torah or wisdom.
I mean even if you don't say things, and you
understand תורה, Torah, right, I understand. But רש״י Rashi just makes it
like, you know, more like a very broad comparison. You know, Oh,
if you're able to keep your secret, you're as weighty as the
סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. You know, it's not as much of this direct... but
you're right, the simple sense of the גמרא is more like you're
saying, that it's more sort of like the wisdom and the wisdom
of תורה, Torah, and you keep it, and you... you know, although
you're not supposed to withhold תורה, Torah, so it's... I think there's
some aspect of this secret wisdom you're not supposed to be sharing.
אמר רבי חנין, Amar Rabbi Chanin, לא נברא יין אלא לנחם אבלים.
lo nivra yayin ela lenachem avelim. So back to the value of
wine. Remember we started with all this discussion about wine helping somebody
learn or פסקן. So now we're saying that the wine was only
created, what's the whole purpose of wine if it leads to all
these negative things? No, it has some good purpose. It was created
to console the mourners. So suppose somebody's really in a bad mood,
you get Of course it's so funny, right, because wine and alcohol
is a depressant, but of course that's what people do, they're depressed
and they go and they drink. So it's for console the mourners,
ולשלם שכר לרשעים, u'leshalem sachar la'resha'im, and to pay back wicked people.
So, meaning,
the way Rashi explains it is that they
get that this
is that they get some reward in this world, as it were,
and not in the world to come. And the reward in this
world is something that also is pretty mixed, as the Gemara's been
saying. What about Kohelet?
שנאמר ויין ישמח חיים.
shenemar ve'yayin
yesamach chayim. ויין
ישמח לבב אנוש.
ve'yayin
yesamach levav enosh.
שנאמר תנו שכר לאובד. shenemar tenu shechar le'oved. Give mead to the
one who is wasting away, or to the wicked person. And the
Maharsha says it's a little play on words: שכר shechar and שכר,
sachar, that is his reward, is that he can get drunk in
this world. Right? And the end of the pasuk is ויין למרי
נפש, ve'yayin le'marei nafesh, and wine to those who are embittered of
soul. אמר רבי חנין בר פפא כל שאין יין נשפך בתוך ביתו
כמים, amar Rabbi Chanin bar Pappa kol she'ein yayin nishpach betoch beito
kemayim, and now here's a countering voice: Anybody whose wine is not
so plentiful in your house that it's not running like water, אינו
בכלל ברכה eino bichlal bracha is not included in the sense of
being blessed. שנאמר וברך את לחמך ואת מימיך. shenemar u'verach et lachmecha
ve'et meimecha. God will bless your bread and your water. מה לחם
שניקח בכסף מעשר שני, ma lechem shenikach be'chesef ma'aser sheni, the same
way bread is something that can be purchased with Ma'aser Sheni money,
אף מים שניקח בכסף מעשר שני, af mayim shenikach be'chesef ma'aser sheni,
it has to mean the type of a liquid that's purchased with
Ma'aser Sheni money, which is not water. ומאי ניהו יין? u'mai nihu
yayin? It's wine. וקרי ליה מים? ve'kari lei mayim? and it's called
water to tell you that the real blessing is that wine is
as plentiful as water. אי נשפך בביתו כמים איכא ברכה. ei nishpach
beveito kemayim ika bracha. If it's poured in your house like water,
it's a blessing. ואי לא לא. ve'ei lo lo. And if not,
no. אמר אילעי. amar Ilai. Says Rabbi Ilai. You might remember him,
he was that one from that whole story with Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel, right? Or it was Rabban Gamliel, he was the one who
was walking behind him, right? And was picking up the—what do you
call it? Not Rabban—Rabban Gamliel, picking up the nice loaves. Anyway, בשלושה
דברים אדם ניכר. bishlosha devarim adam nikar. This is a very famous
Gemara. A person
is—can be distinguished—his character, right, can be seen through three things: בכוסו
ובכיסו ובכעסו. be'choso u've'chiso u've'chaso. How he acts when he's drunk, how
he acts in business, and how he acts when he's angry. So
that's when your true character reveals itself, right? So when you're drunk,
as they say, נכנס יין יצא סוד, nichnas yayin yatza sod, you're
not as much in control, so more of your true self comes
out. When it's in business, that's when money is at stake, so
how you act when there's really money to be made. And בכעסו,
u've'chaso, when you get angry, you're also not as in control, or
the fact about the fact that you do get angry, and how
angry you get, and how you deal with your anger. ואמרי לה
אף בשחקו, ve'amrei lah af bischoko, and some say even in his
joking around, right? What does it—much truth—much seriousness is said in jest?
So when he's—that's when sometimes some of your true character is revealed.
Okay, now back to Halacha. That was a very fascinating
page or half of Agadata. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב. amar Rav
Yehuda amar Rav. ישראל ונוכרי בפנימית
ישראל בחיצונה.
Yisrael ve'nochri
bifnimit Yisrael bechitzona. Let's say you have a Jew and a non-Jew
in an inner courtyard and only a Jew in the outer one.
בא מעשה לפני רבי ואסר. ba ma'aseh lifnei Rebbe ve'asar. So Rabbi
said it's forbidden. לפני רבי חייא ואסר. lifnei Rabbi Chiya ve'asar. Rabbi
Chiya said it's forbidden. So the issue here is, right, it's a
question about two Jews or one Jew. If there's only one Jew,
the non-Jew doesn't matter. So if you've got two courtyards, right? Here's
the street, whatever, and here's the thing. So
the
only way these guys are getting out is
through is through B, right? So here you have this whole courtyard
is owned by one Jew, and here you have a Jew and
a non-Jew. So is it two Jews are living with the non-Jew
and he creates an Eruv problem, or no? Or maybe it's only
one Jew living with the non-Jew. Because these guys, if they want
to get out to the street, have to go there. So in
a way, they're always with this other Jew. Okay, so how do
you account? So let's see what the Gemara says: אסר, asar, which
means it's two Jews. Now, אסר asar for whom? Is it אסר
asar for B or is it also אסר asar even for A?
So the Gemara says like this: יתיב רבה ורב יוסף בשלהי פירקא
דרב ששת. yativ Rabbah ve'Rav Yosef beshilahei pirka de'Rav Sheshet. So Rabbah
and Rav Yosef stayed after the end of Rav Sheshet's shiur. That
idea of hanging—hanging around at the end of a shiur because you
want to, you know, you want to sort of pester the person
who gave the lecture was true even then. So they hang out
at the end of the shiur. ויתיב רב ששת וקאמר. ve'yativ Rav
Sheshet ve'ka'amar. And Rav Sheshet was sitting and saying: כמאן אמר רב
לשמעתיה? keman amar Rav leshmateih? Who is Rav going like that's saying
that this is a problem? כרבי מאיר. ke'Rabbi Meir. Like Rabbi Meir,
who says that even one Jew is a problem, because he assumed
that it wasn't true they weren't seen as being together. So he
says, if that's a problem, it's a problem in courtyard A because
even one Jew is a
problem, not okay. פרכיש רבה רישיה. parchish Rabbah reisheih. Yeah, yeah, that
makes sense. It's going like Rabbi Meir. אמר רב יוסף. amar Rav
Yosef. So said Rav Yosef: תרי גברי רברבי כרבנן ליטעו בהאי מילתא?
trei gavrei ravrevei ke'rabbanan lito behai milta? Two great—two great rabbis like
these rabbis lead to—make such a mistake? אי רבי מאיר, ei Rabbi
Meir, if this was Rabbi Meir who says even one Jew makes
a problem, למה לי ישראל בחיצונה? lama li Yisrael bechitzona? Why do
you have to make this special case that there's a Jew in
the outer courtyard? Just say a Jew and a non-Jew, it's a
problem. וכי תימא מעשה שהיה כך היה? ve'chi teima ma'aseh shehayah kach
hayah? Oh,
maybe that was just the case that was asked, but it really
is immaterial that a guy was in the outer courtyard.
והא ve'ha דבעו מיניה מרב, de'ba'u minei me'Rav, but they asked רב,
Rav, פנימי במקומו מהו, penimi bi'mkomo mahu, what's the story about the
about the inner one in its own place? ואמר להו מותר, ve'amar
lehu mutar, and he said that it's מותר. mutar. What does this
mean? So it says that, hold on let me just get רש״י,
Rashi,
right,
so basically he said, hello, can I
drive by?
I have a truck.
I'm sorry? Can I drive by? Yes. You have a move? Yes.
Okay, so he basically said, they said to רב, Rav, what about
in courtyard A? Okay, so רב Rav said, oh, courtyard A is
fine because there's only one non-Jew. The problem is in courtyard B,
because in courtyard B, every the non, you know, both a Jew
and a non-Jew are going to be going through there, so courtyard
B is like it has all three people, okay? But courtyard A
by itself is fine. So look, if courtyard A by itself is
fine, you see it's not רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, you see that
one non-Jew is just okay. By the way, about like why do
we have this detail if it's not relevant? You know, people don't
realize that a lot of the when you read a תשובה, teshuvah,
I mean not that this is a תשובה, teshuvah, but you know,
the first חידוש chiddush of the תשובה, teshuvah, first it hears the
question and then starts giving the answer, so you figure, okay, like
we're really just starting to get the opinion of the one who
was asked when it gets to be the answer, but no, just
in how you frame the question, how you tell over the question
and which details you see as pertinent and you see as worth
sort of distilling and which ones do you leave out is already
part of your analysis. So here the very fact that it was
given this scenario shows that it was because of the other one.
And anyway, explicitly רב Rav said that the inner courtyard is okay.
So אלא מאי, ella mai, רבי אליעזר בן יעקב? Rebbi Eliezer ben
Yaakov? So who are you saying? It's like רבי אליעזר בן יעקב,
Rebbi Eliezer ben Yaakov, that two are a problem and one is
not? הא אמר עד שיש שני ישראל אוסרין זה על זה, ha
amar ad she'yesh sheni Yisrael osrin zeh al zeh, but the way
he framed it was: only when two Jews make one another forbidden,
which means what? Which means that they're in the same place. Because
if you basically had, ignore the non-Jew, right, what would be the
story if you just had this courtyard and they made an עירוב
eruv and this courtyard made an עירוב eruv and they didn't make
an עירוב eruv together? So this is a famous debate of רבי
עקיבא Rebbi Akiva and the רבנן. Rabbanan. For רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva
says, even though they're מותר במקומן, mutar bi'mkomon, they're אוסר שלא במקומן.
oser she'lo bi'mkomon. Since A goes out through B, it's like A
is in B and B has to make an עירוב eruv together
with A. And the רבנן Rabbanan say, no, if it's something that
is מותר במקומו, mutar bi'mkomo, since A is okay, it's not אוסר
שלא במקומו, oser she'lo bi'mkomo, it doesn't make B problematic. Okay, which
is basically a way of saying, you can look at A and
B separately. Even though A has to go through B, you don't
look at them all together in B. So it says, this is
not שני ישראלים אוסרים זה על זה. sheni Yisraelim osrim zeh al
zeh. If it was all Jews, A would not have an impact
on B. So therefore even if it's a non-Jew here, it should
not have an impact, and therefore B should not be a problem.
והגמרא ve'ha'gemara and the
רבנן Rabbanan do not debate whether A can go into B. Everyone
would say B can't go into A, right? Since they didn't make
an עירוב? eruv?
No,
nobody said you can't carry from A to B. The question is
can you carry in B by itself? Does the fact that A
travels through B mean that B can't make its own עירוב? eruv?
It's not about going from A. If you don't make an עירוב
eruv together you can't carry from A to B or from B
to A. Walking you can always walk where you want, okay, but
it's about carrying. The question is can B carry in its own
courtyard? And the answer would be and the answer according to רבי
עקיבא Rebbi Akiva is no, because unless they've made an עירוב eruv
with A, they can't make their own עירוב. eruv. But the רבנן
Rabbanan say yes.
Or A can always go into B. Just the question is if
they didn't,
right, so you can't carry? Go, walk, anybody can walk where they
want, but you can't carry. It's just a question of whether B
can carry. Nobody can carry in another person's courtyard from your courtyard
unless you've made an עירוב eruv with them. Okay, so you can
only carry in your own courtyard. The question is can B
make their own עירוב eruv to carry in their own courtyard without
A? רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva says they cannot make their own עירוב.
eruv. A is members of their courtyard.
All right, so הגמרא ha'gemara says, so it's not אוסרין, osrin, so
anyway, so הגמרא ha'gemara says, so this shouldn't be a problem because
they cannot, you know, A is not relevant to B. So אלא
לרבי עקיבא, ella le'Rebbi Akiva, fine, we go like רבי עקיבא, Rebbi
Akiva, דאמר רגל המותרת במקומה אוסרת שלא במקומה. de'amar regel ha'muteret bi'mkomah
oseret she'lo bi'mkomah. Although A is permissible in its own space, it
makes troubles for B. So yes, it's according to רבי עקיבא. Rebbi
Akiva. So according to רבי עקיבא, Rebbi Akiva, if it was all
Jews, B would have to make an עירוב eruv together with A.
So similarly if it's a non-Jew, right, in this case where it's
a non-Jew, since B has to make an עירוב eruv together with
A, then it is two Jews living with a non-Jew and then
it's a problem. So it's a fancy way of saying in this
scenario, B's עירוב eruv must include A and that turns it into
two Jews with a non-Jew and that creates the problem.
Okay, and so let's say it was all Jews,
all Jews, B would have to do A but they could do
it. But because there's a non-Jew, okay, then it becomes a problem.
So the חידוש chiddush is not that B has to make an
עירוב eruv with A, it's that once it's making the עירוב eruv
it needs to make with A, then it becomes two Jews with
a non-Jew and it becomes a problem. Okay, so now the גמרא
says like this, למה לי נכרי? אפילו ישראל נמי. Lama li nochri?
Afillu Yisrael nami.
So why do you have to say a non-Jew? Even a Jew,
which is basically saying Michael's point, that you have to always make
an עירוב eruv with A anyway. So let me just double check
רש"י, Rashi, one minute.
Right, meaning anyway you have to make an עירוב eruv together.
So the גמרא says, which is basically what Michael
said, אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע לעולם כרבי אליעזר בן יעקב
וכרבי עקיבא. Amar Rav Huna breide d'Rav Yehoshua, le'olam ke'Rabbi Eliezer ben
Yaakov u'ke'Rabbi Akiva. No, it's like we said, it's Rabbi Eliezer ben
Yaakov, two is a problem, and like Rabbi Akiva, that B makes
a problem on A. והכא במאי עסקינן, V'hacha be'mai askinan, I'm sorry,
A makes a problem on B. And here what are we talking
about? כגון שעירבו. Kegon she'irvu. This is like I responded to Michael,
you see Michael already got our discussion down in the גמרא. Okay,
so yes, A and B are trying to make an עירוב. eruv.
If it was just ישראלים Yisraelim it would be fine.
טעמא דאיכא נכרי דאסיר, Ta'ama de'ika nochri de'asir, it's because of the
non-Jew now it's a problem, אבל ליכא נכרי לא אסיר, aval leka
nochri lo asir, but without him it's not a problem. Okay, so
basically this scenario where A travels through B, according to Rabbi Akiva,
B can only make an עירוב eruv if it does it together
with A. So it did it together with A. Now because of
the non-Jew, if A did it by itself it would be fine
because it's only one Jew. But because when B did it together
with A, it created two Jews, and two Jews and a non-Jew
is now a problem. Okay, so now the גמרא says like this,
בעי מיניה רבי אליעזר מרב. Ba'ei minei Rabbi Eliezer mi'Rav. So Rabbi
Eliezer asked Rav, ישראל ונכרי בחיצונה ישראל בפנימית מהו Yisrael ve'nochri be'chitzona,
Yisrael be'pnimis mai?
Let's say you have a Jew and a non-Jew in the outer
one and only a Jew in the inner one. What's the story
there? So we're reversing.
Okay, and presumably in this case you chose to make an
עירוב eruv because you would have to. Right? You wouldn't have to
make an עירוב eruv in this case, A with B, A can
make their own עירוב, eruv, but for some reason, is this the
way I had A and B last time? Okay. So here you
have Jew
and
non-Jew and here you've got Jew. Okay, oh no I'm sorry, I
take that back. You have to, for B to carry you have
to make an עירוב, eruv, right? Okay, because same story, right? Somebody's
going through. For B to carry you have to make an עירוב
eruv together with A. You made an עירוב eruv with A. Should
B now be a problem because it's two Jews with a non-Jew?
It should seem to be the same thing. So let's see what
the גמרא says.
ישראל ונכרי בחיצונה וישראל בפנימית
מהו
Yisrael ve'nochri be'chitzona ve'Yisrael
be'pnimis mai? התם טעמא משום דשכיחי דדיירי. Hasam ta'ama mishum deshchichi dedairi.
In the first scenario, right remember what's the reason two is worse
is because it's a more common case. So in the first scenario
it's more common that you would have the Jew and the non-Jew
on the inside and a Jew on the outside, meaning that the
Jew on the inside, the question is would the Jew be afraid
of living together with a non-Jew without there being another Jew around?
So the גמרא says it's more common that this case he'd more
be afraid than the reverse case than when they're on the inside.
Why? Let's take a look. You would think there you're exposed more
to רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, less to be afraid about, but let's
see what the גמרא says. התם היינו טעמא משום דשכיח דדיירי. Hasam
hainu ta'ama mishum deshchiach dedairi.
In the earlier case where they're both on the inside, that's more
common that he would be, he'd be less afraid. Why? דמירתת נכרי.
demirsas nochri. That the non-Jew would be afraid to do anything to
the Jew, we're concerned about murder here. וסבר השתא אתי ישראל. Vesavar,
hashta asi Yisrael. The Jew from the outer courtyard will come. ואמר
ליה ישראל דהוה גבך היכא Ve'amar lei, Yisrael dehavi gabach heicha? Where's
your Jewish neighbor? And I can't say oh he's out at the
marketplace because I would have seen him, he would have had to
walk through. אבל הכא, Aval hacha, here, where the Jew and the
non-Jew are on the outer courtyard, אמינא, amina, if the other Jew
asks me where's your neighbor I'll say נגד ואזל ליה. nagad ve'azal
lei. Yeah, he went out, he's out at the market or something.
So maybe this case is less common, the Jew would be afraid
to be in the courtyard in this case. או דילמא הכא נמי
מירתת. O dilma hacha nami mirsas. Or here too he'd be afraid.
וסבר השתא אתי ישראל וחזי לי. Vesavar, hashta asi Yisrael vechazi li.
He'll always be afraid of doing something because the guy from the
back courtyard might be walking through and seeing what I'm doing. אמרי
ליה תן לחכם ויחכם עוד. Amrei lei, ten le'chacham ve'yechkam od. Give
to the wise person and he will be wise further, you know,
he'll figure it out. Meaning figure it out yourself, but also the
idea is is that it's more like the same. Yes, it's the
same הלכה. halakha. So in both cases it becomes like two ישראלים
Yisraelim and we're not saying one is less common and therefore not
part of the two ישראל Yisrael category. ריש לקיש ותלמידי דרבי חנינא,
Reish Lakish ve'talmidei de'Rabbi Chanina, Reish Lakish and the students of Rabbi
Chanina, איקלעו לההוא פונדק. iklei le'hahu pundak. They came to a certain
inn. ולא הוה שוכר. Ve'lo havah socher. And the person who was,
there were multiple rooms in the inn, this is actually the common
case of an apartment building, so this is actually going to be
very important הלכה להלכה. halakha le'halakha. So there were multiple rooms in
the inn and one of them was rented by a non-Jew
and they would have rented from him, right, they would have made
an עירוב eruv within the inn or the inn and all the
other members of the courtyard. Okay, but the person who had rented
the room wasn't around. דהוה משכיר. Dehavah maskir. And the renter, the
landlord, whatever, he was there. So the question is can you do
a deal with the landlord? Right, how do we do an עירוב
eruv now in our city with all the non-Jews? Okay. Basically do
a deal with the city. What about all the people that own
property? So we'll talk about it, but anyway, here, here's the foundation
of that. אמרו, amru, they said, מהוי ליה מיניה, mahvei lei minei,
can we just rent from the landlord even though the person who
really has rented the room and has rights to the room is
not here? So כל היכא דלא מצי מסלק ליה, kol heicha d'la
matzi mesalek lei, if the landlord can't get the guy to leave
his room, like he can't say I'm switching your room and the
guy wouldn't have a say, if he can't, let me reframe it,
if he could say I'm sorry, I need this room, I'm going
to move you to a different room, and the guy couldn't protest,
then obviously the landlord still has control and the room is, and
he's in a position to rent. So לא תיבעי לך, lo tibaye
lach, then I don't have a question. If landlord can't do that,
דלא אגרינן, d'lo agrinan, that I can't rent from the landlord. כי
תיבעי, ki tibaye, what do I want to know? היכא דמצי מסלק
ליה, heicha d'matzi mesalek lei, if landlord could move the guy, מאי,
mai, what do we say? כיון דמצי מסלק אגרינן, keivan d'matzi mesalek
agrinan, since he can remove him, I can rent from the landlord,
או דילמא, o dilma, or perhaps השתא מיהא הלא סליק, hashta miha
halo salik, right now he hasn't removed the guy and the guy
currently does have rights to the room and I can't make the
deal with the landlord.
So אמר ליה ריש לקיש, amar lei Reish Lakish, so Reish Lakish
said, you know what, נשכור, niskor, look, it's about to be Shabbos,
we can't figure this whole thing out, let's just rent from the
landlord, וכשנגיע אצל רבותינו שבדרום, u'keshenagia etzel raboteinu shebadarom,
when we come to our masters in the south, נשאל להם, nishal
lahem, we'll ask them. So, you know, so, I mean, and now
okay, but how could they do it if they didn't know the
halacha? So Rashi says because it's דרבנן derabanan and הלכה כדברי המיקל
בבבל, halacha kedivrei hameikel b'Bavel, בבבל בעירוב, be'Bavel be'eiruv,
and therefore they were willing to assume, you know what, it might
work, so let's assume that it does and let's do it and
then we'll ask afterwards.
So אתו שיילוה לרב אפס, atu shayluh l'Rav Afes, they went and
they asked Rav Afes. אמר להם, amar lahem, יפה עשיתם ששכרתם, yafe
asitem shesechartem, oh, you did good. Okay, so that works, it does
work to rent from the landlord as long as he has certain
rights in the actual apartment itself, in the actual room itself. And
we'll continue this tomorrow and discuss, really this is highly relevant about,
you know, about the type of way we do an עירוב eiruv
and renting from the city and not from the individual people. Who
is the one you can sort of do the deal with?
You also have hotels, an hotel,
and boats, and apartments.